Bacteria are the oldest living organisms on the earth.
البكتيريا هي أقدم الكائنات الحية على وجه الارض
They've been here for billions of years,
وجودها يعود لبلايين السنين
and what they are are single-celled microscopic organisms.
و هي عبارة عن كائنات مجهرية وحيدة الخلية
So they are one cell and they have this special property
فإذاً هي وحيدة الخلية ولها خاصية مميزة
that they only have one piece of DNA.
فهي تحتوي على جزيئ "دي ان ايه" واحد
They have very few genes,
وهي أيضاً تحتوي على جينات ومعلومات جينية قليلة جداً
and genetic information to encode all of the traits that they carry out.
للقيام بكل الخصائص التي تنفذها
And the way bacteria make a living
و تستمر البكتيريا في الحياه عن طريق
is that they consume nutrients from the environment,
استهلاكها للمواد المغذيه من البيئة المحيطة بها
they grow to twice their size, they cut themselves down in the middle,
تنمو البكتيريا الى ضعف حجمها ثم تقوم بالانقسام من النصف
and one cell becomes two, and so on and so on.
مكونه خليتين من الخلية الاصل، ثم تستمر هذه العمليه بالتكرار
They just grow and divide, and grow and divide -- so a kind of boring life,
هي تنمو وتنقسم، تنمو وتنقسم -- حياه مملة نوعاً ما
except that what I would argue is that you have
بإستثناء اني سوف أجادل و أقول بأن لديكم
an amazing interaction with these critters.
تفاعل مذهل مع هذه الكائنات
I know you guys think of yourself as humans, and this is sort of how I think of you.
انا أدرك أنكم تنظرون لأنفسكم كبشر، وهذا تقريباً كيف أفكر بكم
This man is supposed to represent
هذا الرجل يُفترض أن يمثل
a generic human being,
كائن بشري بصفة عامة
and all of the circles in that man are all of the cells that make up your body.
وكل الدوائر في هذا الرجل هي عبارة عن الخلايا التي تتركب منها أجسامنا
There is about a trillion human cells that make each one of us
هناك ما يقارب التريليون خلية بشرية تدخل في تركيب كل واحد منا
who we are and able to do all the things that we do,
تحدد من نحن و كيف نقوم بكل ما نقوم به
but you have 10 trillion bacterial cells
ولكن لديك عشره تريليونات خلية بكتيرية عليك
in you or on you at any moment in your life.
أو داخل جسمك في ايه لحظة في حياتك
So, 10 times more bacterial cells
هذا يعني وجود خلايا بكتيرية أكثر بعشرة أضعاف
than human cells on a human being.
عن الخلايا البشرية على الانسان
And of course it's the DNA that counts,
و بالطبع تعود الاهمية لل "دي ان ايه"
so here's all the A, T, Gs and Cs
فهنا توجد أجزائها
that make up your genetic code, and give you all your charming characteristics.
التي تكوّن شفرتك الجينية، و تعطيك كل مواصفاتك الفاتنة
You have about 30,000 genes.
عندك ما يقارب الثلاثين ألف جين
Well it turns out you have 100 times more bacterial genes
حسناً هذا يعني ان لديك مائة مرة أكثر من الجينات البكتيرية
playing a role in you or on you all of your life.
تلعب دوراً في جسمك او عليك طيلة حياتك
At the best, you're 10 percent human,
في أفضل الأحوال، أنتم عشره بالمائه بشر
but more likely about one percent human,
ولكن الأرجح حوالي واحد بالمائه بشر
depending on which of these metrics you like.
اعتماداً على المقياس الذي تستخدمونه
I know you think of yourself as human beings,
انا ادرك إنكم تنظرون لانفسكم كبشر
but I think of you as 90 or 99 percent bacterial.
ولكن انا اراكم تسعون او تسعه و تسعون بالمائه بكتريا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
These bacteria are not passive riders,
هذه البكتيريا ليست من النوع غير الفعال
these are incredibly important, they keep us alive.
هي مهمه بشكل لا يصدق، وتساهم في بقائنا على قيد الحياة
They cover us in an invisible body armor
تغطيني بدرع جسدي خفي
that keeps environmental insults out
وتمنع عنى أذى البيئة المحيطة بي
so that we stay healthy.
كي نبقى بصحة جيدة
They digest our food, they make our vitamins,
هي التي تقوم بهضم طعامنا وانتاج الفيتامينات
they actually educate your immune system
هي في الواقع من يثقف نظام المناعة لدينا
to keep bad microbes out.
كي تبقى الميكروبات السيئة خارج اجسامنا
So they do all these amazing things
اذاً هي تقوم بكل هذه الأمور المذهلة
that help us and are vital for keeping us alive,
التي تساعدنا وايضا أساسيه للبقاء على قيد الحياه
and they never get any press for that.
ولا تحصل على الشهرة لقيامها بكل هذا
But they get a lot of press because they do a lot of
ولكن تحصل على الشهرة للقيام بكثير من
terrible things as well.
الأمور الفظيعه.
So, there's all kinds of bacteria on the Earth
هناك الكثير من أنواع البكتيريا في العالم
that have no business being in you or on you at any time,
التي لايستحسن وجودها داخل اجسامنا او علينا في اي وقت
and if they are, they make you incredibly sick.
وان كانت موجودة فستجعلنا مرضى بشكل لايصدق
And so, the question for my lab is whether you want to think about all the
وبالتالي، السؤال من مختبرنا هو اذا ماكنتم تريدون التفكير في الموضوع ككل
good things that bacteria do, or all the bad things that bacteria do.
الامور الحسنة التي تقوم بها البكتيريا، او الامور السيئة
The question we had is how could they do anything at all?
السؤال الذي طرحناه هو كيف بآستطاعتها القيام بأي شي على الاطلاق
I mean they're incredibly small,
ما اقصده هو انها صغيره بشكل لا يصدق
you have to have a microscope to see one.
يجب عليك استخدام المجهر لتراها
They live this sort of boring life where they grow and divide,
إنها تعيش حياة مملة الى حد ما حيث تقوم بالنمو والانقسام
and they've always been considered to be these asocial reclusive organisms.
ودائما ما إعتبرت كائنات منعزلة و منحازة لنفسها
And so it seemed to us that they are just too small to have an impact
ولهذا بدا بأنها على درجه من الصغر تمنعها
on the environment
من ترك اي اثر على البيئة
if they simply act as individuals.
إذا ببساطة تصرفت بشكل فردي
And so we wanted to think if there couldn't be a different
ولهاذا شآنا ان نفكر اذا ماكانت هناك
way that bacteria live.
طريقة أخرى تعيش فيها البكتيريا
The clue to this came from another marine bacterium,
الدليل على هذا اتى من نوع آخر من البكتيريا البحريه
and it's a bacterium called Vibrio fischeri.
وهذا النوع يدعى فيبريو فيشري
What you're looking at on this slide is just a person from my lab
الذي تنظرون اليه على الشاشه الآن هو شخص من مختبرنا
holding a flask of a liquid culture of a bacterium,
يحمل زجاجه تحتوي على سائل البكتيريا المزروعة في المختبر
a harmless beautiful bacterium that comes from the ocean,
انه نوع من البكتيريا الجميله غير المؤذيه التي تأتي من المحيط
named Vibrio fischeri.
تسمى فيبريو فيشري
This bacterium has the special property that it makes light,
هذه البكتيريا لديها خاصية مميزة وهي إنها مضيئة
so it makes bioluminescence,
فهي تقوم بالإضاءة الحيوية
like fireflies make light.
بنفس الطريقه التي تقوم بها حشره سراج الليل
We're not doing anything to the cells here.
نحن لم نقم بعمل اي شئ للخلايا
We just took the picture by turning the lights off in the room,
لقد قمنا فقط بأخذ الصورة بعد إطفاء النور بالغرفة
and this is what we see.
وهذا مانراه هنا.
What was actually interesting to us
في الحقيقة، الشيء الذي اثار انتباهنا
was not that the bacteria made light,
لم يكن ان البكتيريا قادره على الاضاءة
but when the bacteria made light.
ولكن هو أنه متى ما تضيء البكتيريا
What we noticed is when the bacteria were alone,
ما لاحظناه هو انه عندما تكون خلايا البكتيريا منفردة
so when they were in dilute suspension, they made no light.
اي عندما تكون بنسب ضئيلة و منعزلة عن بعضها لا تضيء
But when they grew to a certain cell number
ولكن عندما تزداد بالعدد و تتجمع الى حد معين
all the bacteria turned on light simultaneously.
كل البكتيريا تضيء في وقت واحد
The question that we had is how can bacteria, these primitive organisms,
السؤال الذي يطرح نفسه هوكيف بإستطاعة هذه الكائنات البدائية
tell the difference from times when they're alone,
أن تعرف الفرق بين وجودها في حالة منفردة
and times when they're in a community,
وبين وجودها في جماعات
and then all do something together.
والقيام بشيء بشكل جماعي
What we've figured out is that the way that they do that is that they talk to each other,
والذي استنتجناه هو انه بإستطاعتها القيام بهذا عن طريق التحدث مع بعضها البعض
and they talk with a chemical language.
وهذا الكلام هو عن طريق لغة كيميائية
This is now supposed to be my bacterial cell.
سأفترض ان هذه خليتي البكتيرية
When it's alone it doesn't make any light.
وهي منفردة لاتقوم بعمل اي ضوء
But what it does do is to make and secrete small molecules
ولكن ما تقوم به هوعمل جزيئات صغيرة و سرية
that you can think of like hormones,
بإستطاعتكم ان تفكروا بها كهرمونات
and these are the red triangles, and when the bacteria is alone
وهي المثلثات الحمراء وعندما تكون البكتيريا منفردة
the molecules just float away and so no light.
تنتشر هذه الجزيئات فلا يكون هناك أي ضوء
But when the bacteria grow and double
ولكن حينما تنمو البكتيريا وتتضاعف
and they're all participating in making these molecules,
وكلها تقوم بالمشاركة بعمل هذه الجزيئات
the molecule -- the extracellular amount of that molecule
الجزيئ - النسبة الخارجيه للجزيء
increases in proportion to cell number.
تزداد بنسبه طردية لعدد الخلايا
And when the molecule hits a certain amount
وعند وصول عدد الجزيئات إلى نسبة معينة
that tells the bacteria how many neighbors there are,
هذا يوضح للبكتيريا كمية البكتيريا المجاورة
they recognize that molecule
باستطاعة البكتيريا فهم هذا الجزيء
and all of the bacteria turn on light in synchrony.
ثم تقوم البكتيريا بالاضاءة بطريقة منسقة
That's how bioluminescence works --
هذه هي الطريقه التي تعمل بها الاضاءة الحيوية
they're talking with these chemical words.
تتكلم مع بعضها عن طريق كلمات كيميائية
The reason that Vibrio fischeri is doing that comes from the biology.
السبب وراء قيام الفيبريو فيشري بهذا يأتي من علم الاحياء
Again, another plug for the animals in the ocean,
للمره الثانيه دعايه اخرى للحيوانات البحرية
Vibrio fischeri lives in this squid.
الفيبريو فيشري تعيش داخل الحبار
What you are looking at is the Hawaiian Bobtail Squid,
الذي تنظرون اليه هو الحبار ذو الذيل القصير من هاواي
and it's been turned on its back,
وهو مقلوب على ظهره
and what I hope you can see are these two glowing lobes
وما آمل ان تروه هو هذان الجزئان المتوهجان
and these house the Vibrio fischeri cells,
هما الجزء الذي يحمل خلايا الفيبريو فيشري
they live in there, at high cell number
التي تعيش بكميات كبيره بالداخل
that molecule is there, and they're making light.
الجزيئات موجوده وهي التي تقوم بالاضاءه
The reason the squid is willing to put up with these shenanigans
وسبب تحمل الحبار لهذا التطفل
is because it wants that light.
هو حاجته لهذا الضوء
The way that this symbiosis works
الطريقه التي يعمل بها هذا التكافل
is that this little squid lives just off the coast of Hawaii,
هو ان هذا الحبار يعيش على سواحل هاواي
just in sort of shallow knee-deep water.
في مياه ضحله تصل الى حد الركبة
The squid is nocturnal, so during the day
هذا الحبارهو من النوع الليلي ففي اثناء النهار
it buries itself in the sand and sleeps,
يدفن نفسه في الرمل و ينام
but then at night it has to come out to hunt.
ولكن في الليل يجب عليه الخروج للصيد
On bright nights when there is lots of starlight or moonlight
في الليالي المضيئه المليئة بنور القمر
that light can penetrate the depth of the water
باستطاعة الضوء اختراق عمق الماء
the squid lives in, since it's just in those couple feet of water.
التي يعيش فيها الحبار بما أنها مجرد اقدام من الماء
What the squid has developed is a shutter
لقد قام الحبار بتطوير محبس ضوء
that can open and close over this specialized light organ housing the bacteria.
بامكنه الفتح و الاغلاق على العضو المتخصص بالضوء الحامل للبكتيريا
Then it has detectors on its back
ثم يوجد على ظهره مجسات
so it can sense how much starlight or moonlight is hitting its back.
مما يعطيه القدره على الاحساس بكمية ضوء النجوم او القمر على ظهره
And it opens and closes the shutter
ويقوم بفتح و اغلاق المحبس
so the amount of light coming out of the bottom --
ولكي تكون نسبه الضوء الخارجه من الاسفل
which is made by the bacterium --
والتي تنتجها البكتيريا
exactly matches how much light hits the squid's back,
تعادل تماما نسبه الضوء التي تضرب ظهر الحبار
so the squid doesn't make a shadow.
وبهذه الطريقه يستطيع الحبار اخفاء ظله
It actually uses the light from the bacteria
في الحقيقه هو يقوم باستخدام الضوء من البكتيريا
to counter-illuminate itself in an anti-predation device
ليعكس الضوء عن نفسه صانعا أداة تقيه من أن يُفترس
so predators can't see its shadow,
لكي لاترى الحيوانات المفترسه ظله
calculate its trajectory, and eat it.
فتقوم بتحديد مسيرته و تلتهمه
This is like the stealth bomber of the ocean.
انه مثل قاذفة القنابل المتسللة لكن في البحر
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But then if you think about it, the squid has this terrible problem
ولكن اذا امعنت التفكيرستجد ان لدى الحبار مشكلة كبيرة
because it's got this dying, thick culture of bacteria
لأن لديه مجموعة من البكتيريا تشارف على الموت
and it can't sustain that.
وهو لايستطيع تحمل هذا
And so what happens is every morning when the sun comes up
الذي يحدث هو انه في كل صباح عند شروق الشمس
the squid goes back to sleep, it buries itself in the sand,
يغمر الحبار نفسه بالرمل و يذهب للنوم
and it's got a pump that's attached to its circadian rhythm,
ولديه مضخة متصلة بالإيقاع اليومي له
and when the sun comes up it pumps out like 95 percent of the bacteria.
وعند شروق الشمس تضخ خمس و تسعون بالمئة من البكتيريا للخارج
Now the bacteria are dilute, that little hormone molecule is gone,
الان البكتيريا بنسبة ضئيلة فبالتالي لا تقوم بافراز ذلك الهرمون
so they're not making light --
وبالتالي لاتصنع الضوء
but of course the squid doesn't care. It's asleep in the sand.
ولكن بالطبع هذا لايهم الحبار. لانه نائم في الرمل
And as the day goes by the bacteria double,
وبخلال مرور اليوم تتضاعف البكتيريا
they release the molecule, and then light comes on
وتفرز الهرمون، وتعود الإضاءه
at night, exactly when the squid wants it.
في الليل تماما عندما يحتاج الحبار لها.
First we figured out how this bacterium does this,
أولا قمنا بفهم طريقة قيام البكتيريا بهذا
but then we brought the tools of molecular biology to this
ثم إستعنا بوسائل من البيولوجيا الجزيئية
to figure out really what's the mechanism.
لكي نفهم حقا الاليه وراء هذه العملية.
And what we found -- so this is now supposed to be, again, my bacterial cell --
وما عثرنا عليه لنفترض مره اخرى ان هذه خلييتي البكتيريه
is that Vibrio fischeri has a protein --
ان الفيبريو فيشري لديه بروتين
that's the red box -- it's an enzyme that makes
وهو الصندوق الاحمر - انا إنزيمة تقوم بصنع
that little hormone molecule, the red triangle.
جزيء الهرمون الصغير - المثلث الاحمر
And then as the cells grow, they're all releasing that molecule
واثناء نمو الخلايا، تقوم جميعها بافراز ذلك الجزيء
into the environment, so there's lots of molecule there.
في بيئتها المحيطة، فبالتالي يزداد عدد الجزيئات
And the bacteria also have a receptor on their cell surface
وللبكتيريا ايضا جهاز استقبال على سطح الخليه
that fits like a lock and key with that molecule.
الذي يلائم ذلك الجزيئ كالمفتاح والقفل
These are just like the receptors on the surfaces of your cells.
هؤلاء تماما مثل اجهزه الاستقبال الموجده على اسطح خلاياك
When the molecule increases to a certain amount --
عندما يزداد عدد الجزيئات الى حد معين
which says something about the number of cells --
مما يدل على شيء بالنسبه لعدد الخلايا
it locks down into that receptor
فهي تثبت في اسفل جهاز الاستقبال
and information comes into the cells
فتصل المعلومات الى الخلايا
that tells the cells to turn on
وذلك يعلمها بوجوب الاضاءه
this collective behavior of making light.
وهوالسلوك الجماعي المتعلق بالإضاءة
Why this is interesting is because in the past decade
وسبب إثاره هذا الموضوع للاهتمام هو انه خلال العقد الماضي
we have found that this is not just some anomaly
اكتشفنا ان هذا ليس مجرد شذوذ
of this ridiculous, glow-in-the-dark bacterium that lives in the ocean --
من نوع بكتيريا تافهه تعيش في المحيط وتضيئ في الظلام
all bacteria have systems like this.
كل انواع البكتيريا لديها نظام شبيه
So now what we understand is that all bacteria can talk to each other.
وبالتالي ادركنا الان أن باستطاعة البكتيريا التواصل مع بعضها
They make chemical words, they recognize those words,
عن طريق القاء كلمات كيميائية، بإستطاعتها فهمها
and they turn on group behaviors
وتقوم بتفعيل السلوك الجماعي
that are only successful when all of the cells participate in unison.
وتنجح في هذا فقط عن طريق مشاركه كل الخلايا معا بانسجام
We have a fancy name for this: we call it quorum sensing.
اخترنا لهذه العمليه اسم ممتاز، سميناها إدراك النصاب
They vote with these chemical votes,
تقوم بالتصويت عن طريق الاصوات الكيميائيه
the vote gets counted, and then everybody responds to the vote.
وتحصي الاصوات، وبعد ذلك تقوم جميعها بالرد على التصويت
What's important for today's talk
المهم بالنسبه لمحاضره اليوم
is that we know that there are hundreds of behaviors
ان نعرف ان هناك مئات من السلوكيات
that bacteria carry out in these collective fashions.
التي تقوم بها البكتيريا بنفس الطريقه الجماعية
But the one that's probably the most important to you is virulence.
ولكن من المحتمل انه اكثر ما يثير اهتمامكم هو النوع الخبيث منها
It's not like a couple bacteria get in you
اذا هذا لايعني بضعه من البكتيريا تدخل في جسمك
and they start secreting some toxins --
و تبدا بافراز المواد السامه فيه
you're enormous, that would have no effect on you. You're huge.
انت هائل الحجم، وبالتالي هذا لن يؤثر
What they do, we now understand,
الذي تقوم البكتيريا فعله كما ندرك الان
is they get in you, they wait, they start growing,
هو انها تدخل في جسمك، و تنتظر، و تبدا بالتكاثر
they count themselves with these little molecules,
تقوم باحصاء عددها عن طريق تلك الجزيئات الصغيره
and they recognize when they have the right cell number
وباستطاعتها ان تميز وقت بلوغ عدد خلايا كافي
that if all of the bacteria launch their virulence attack together,
بانه اذا قامت كل البكتيريا بالهجوم الضار في آن واحد
they are going to be successful at overcoming an enormous host.
سوف تنجح بهزم الجسم المضيف لها مع ضخامة حجمه
Bacteria always control pathogenicity with quorum sensing.
البكتيريا دائما تتحكم بالامراض عن طريق ادراك النصاب
That's how it works.
وهذه هي الطريقة التي تعمل بها.
We also then went to look at what are these molecules --
بعد ذلك ذهبنا بالنظر الى نوعية هذه الجزيئات
these were the red triangles on my slides before.
تلك المثلثات الحمراء التي رأيتموها في شرائح العرض
This is the Vibrio fischeri molecule.
هذا هو جزيء الفيبريو فيشري
This is the word that it talks with.
هذه هي الكلمة التي تتكلم بها
So then we started to look at other bacteria,
ومن ثم بدأنا بالبحث في انواع اخرى من البكتيريا
and these are just a smattering of the molecules that we've discovered.
وهذه فقط صوره سطحيّة عن الجزيئات التي وجدناها
What I hope you can see
ما ارغب بان تشاهدوه
is that the molecules are related.
هو ان هناك علاقه تربط الجزيئات ببعضها البعض
The left-hand part of the molecule is identical
الجزء الايسر من كل جزيء متطابق
in every single species of bacteria.
في كل صنف من انواع البكتيريا
But the right-hand part of the molecule is a little bit different in every single species.
ولكن يوجد في الجزء الايمن من الجزيء اختلاف بسيط في كل الاصناف
What that does is to confer
وهذا يقوم على منح
exquisite species specificities to these languages.
الاصناف المميزه خصائص لهذه اللغات
Each molecule fits into its partner receptor and no other.
كل جزيء يلائم جهاز الاستقبال الموجود عند شريكه فقط لاغير
So these are private, secret conversations.
اذا فهذه محادثات خاصة وسرية
These conversations are for intraspecies communication.
وهي محادثات للإتِّصَال بين جزيئات من صنف واحد
Each bacteria uses a particular molecule that's its language
كل بكتريا تستخدم جزيئاً محدداً ليكون لغه لها
that allows it to count its own siblings.
والذي يمكِّنها من احصاء عدد أقربائها
Once we got that far we thought
وعندما وصلنا الى هذه المرحلة ادركنا
we were starting to understand that bacteria have these social behaviors.
لقد بدأنا نفهم ان للبكتيريا هذا السلوك الاجتماعي
But what we were really thinking about is that most of the time
ولكن ما كنا فعلا نفكر به هو انه في معظم الاوقات
bacteria don't live by themselves, they live in incredible mixtures,
لاتعيش البكتيريا لوحدها، بل تعيش في تمازج هائل
with hundreds or thousands of other species of bacteria.
مع مئات بل آلاف الأصناف الأخرى من البكتيريا
And that's depicted on this slide. This is your skin.
وهذا موضح في شريحه العرض. هذا هو جلد الانسان
So this is just a picture -- a micrograph of your skin.
اذا هذه فقط مجرد صورة - هي ميكروجراف لجلدك
Anywhere on your body, it looks pretty much like this,
كل مكان في جسمك، يشبه هذه الصورة
and what I hope you can see is that there's all kinds of bacteria there.
وما اود ان تروه هو انه يوجد كل انواع البكتيريا هناك
And so we started to think if this really is about communication in bacteria,
بدأنا نرى اذا ماكان هذا كله من اجل التواصل بين البكتيريا
and it's about counting your neighbors,
ومن اجل احصاء عدد الجيران
it's not enough to be able to only talk within your species.
لايكفي ان تكون فقط قادراً على الكلام ضمن نفس الصنف
There has to be a way to take a census
لابد من وجود وسيله لاخذ إحصاء رسمي
of the rest of the bacteria in the population.
لبقيه اصناف البكتيريا المتواجدة
So we went back to molecular biology
ولهذا عدنا الى الاحياء الجزيئية
and started studying different bacteria,
وبدأنا بدراسة انواع اخرى من البكتيريا
and what we've found now is that
وتوصلنا الى انه
in fact, bacteria are multilingual.
في الحقيقه، البكتيريا متعددة اللغات
They all have a species-specific system --
لديها كلها نظام خاص بكل صنف
they have a molecule that says "me."
اي لديها جزيء يدعى "أنا"
But then, running in parallel to that is a second system
ولكن هذا النظام يعمل بتواز مع نظام آخر
that we've discovered, that's generic.
اكتشفناه وهو نظام شامل.
So, they have a second enzyme that makes a second signal
فاذا لديها إنزيمة اخرى تقوم بعمل إشاره اخرى
and it has its own receptor,
ولديها جهازاستقبال خاص بها
and this molecule is the trade language of bacteria.
وهذا الجزيء هو لغه التعامُل بين البكتيريا
It's used by all different bacteria
تستخدم بين انواع البكتيريا المختلفة
and it's the language of interspecies communication.
وهذه هي لغه الإتِّصَال بين صنف واحد
What happens is that bacteria are able to count
الذي يحدث هو ان البكتيريا قادره على احصاء
how many of me and how many of you.
اعداد صنفها و الاصناف الاخرى منها
They take that information inside,
تاخذ هذه المعلومات للداخل،
and they decide what tasks to carry out
و تقرر المهمه التي ستقوم بها
depending on who's in the minority and who's in the majority
اعتماداً على من لديه نسبه الاغلبيه ومن لديه نسبه الاقليه
of any given population.
من اي تعداد سكاني
Then again we turn to chemistry,
ثم نعود للكيمياء مره اخرى
and we figured out what this generic molecule is --
حيث قمنا باكتشاف ماهو هذا الجزيء الشامل
that was the pink ovals on my last slide, this is it.
وذلك هو الجسيم البيضوي الوردي في شريحة العرض السابقة
It's a very small, five-carbon molecule.
هو عباره عن جزيء يتكون من خمس عناصر كربون
What the important thing is that we learned
و الشيء المهم الذي ادركناه
is that every bacterium has exactly the same enzyme
هو ان كل بكتيريا لديها نفس الانزيم بالضبط
and makes exactly the same molecule.
و تقوم بعمل نفس الجزيء بالضبط
So they're all using this molecule
اذا فجميعها يستخدم نفس هذا الجزيء
for interspecies communication.
للإتصال بين اصناف الجنس الواحد
This is the bacterial Esperanto.
هذه هي لغه الاسبرانتو للبكتيريا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Once we got that far, we started to learn
عندما و صلنا الى هذه المرحلة، بدانا ندرك أن
that bacteria can talk to each other with this chemical language.
بإستطاعة البكتيريا التواصل مع بعضها البعض عن طريق اللغة الكيميائية
But what we started to think is that maybe there is something
ولكن مابدانا نفكر به هو احتمال وجود شيء
practical that we can do here as well.
عملي بامكاننا القيام به ايضاً
I've told you that bacteria do have all these social behaviors,
لقد سبق ان قلت لكم ان للبكتريا سلوكيات اجتماعية متعددة
they communicate with these molecules.
تتصل عن طريق الجزيئات
Of course, I've also told you that one of the important things they do
و بالطبع، قلت لكم ايضا انه من الامور المهمة التي تقوم بها
is to initiate pathogenicity using quorum sensing.
انها تبدا عمليه العدوى بالامراض عن طريق ادراك النصاب
We thought, what if we made these bacteria
فكرنا بان نقوم بجعل هذه البكتيريا
so they can't talk or they can't hear?
غير قادره على الكلام او السمع
Couldn't these be new kinds of antibiotics?
فهل يمكن ان تكون هذه نوعية جديدة للمضاد الحيوي
Of course, you've just heard and you already know
بالطبع لقد سمعت للتو او كنت تعرف
that we're running out of antibiotics.
انه لم يعد لدينا الكثير من المضاد الحيوي
Bacteria are incredibly multi-drug-resistant right now,
البكتيريا الآن قادرة على مقاومة مختلف انواع الدواء بشكل فعال
and that's because all of the antibiotics that we use kill bacteria.
والسبب هو ان المضاد الحيوي الذي نستخدمه يقتل البكتيريا
They either pop the bacterial membrane,
عن طريق فقع الغشاء البكتيري
they make the bacterium so it can't replicate its DNA.
مما يمنع تكاثرال "دي ان ايه" في البكتيريا
We kill bacteria with traditional antibiotics
حاليا نقضي على البكتيريا باستخدام المضاد الحيوي التقليدي
and that selects for resistant mutants.
وذلك ينتقي بديل مقاوم
And so now of course we have this global problem
ولذلك يوجد لدينا الان مشكلة عالمية
in infectious diseases.
متعلقة بالامراض المعدية
We thought, well what if we could sort of do behavior modifications,
فكرنا انه اذا نجحنا بتعديل سلوك البكتيريا نوعا ما
just make these bacteria so they can't talk, they can't count,
اذا استطعنا ان نمنع البكتيريا من الكلام، فلن تستطيع إحصاء عددها
and they don't know to launch virulence.
وباتالي لن تستطيع إطلاق المرض
And so that's exactly what we've done, and we've sort of taken two strategies.
وهذا بالضبط ماقمنا بفعله، وذلك عن طريق اخذ ستراتيجيتين
The first one is we've targeted
الاولى ركزنا فيها على
the intraspecies communication system.
نظام الاتصال بين صنف واحد
So we made molecules that look kind of like the real molecules --
فقمنا بعمل جزيئات شبيهه بالجزيئات الاصليه
which you saw -- but they're a little bit different.
والتي رأيتموها سابقا ولكن مختلفة قليلا عنها
And so they lock into those receptors,
وبالتالي تثبت الجزيئات على جهاز الاستقبال
and they jam recognition of the real thing.
و تقوم بإعاقه التعرف على الجزيء الاصلي
By targeting the red system,
عن طريق استهداف النظام الاحمر
what we are able to do is to make
لقد استطعنا ان ننتج
species-specific, or disease-specific, anti-quorum sensing molecules.
جزيئات مضاده لادراك النصاب خاصة بصنف معين او مرض معين
We've also done the same thing with the pink system.
وقمنا بتطبيق نفس الشيئ على النظام الوردي
We've taken that universal molecule and turned it around a little bit
قمنا بأخذ الجزيئ الشامل و عدّلنا عليه بعض الشيء
so that we've made antagonists
بحيث اننا انتجنا خصماً
of the interspecies communication system.
لنظام الاتصال بين الأصناف
The hope is that these will be used as broad-spectrum antibiotics
نأمل على ان نستخدمه كطيف واسع من المضادات الحيوية
that work against all bacteria.
ليكون مضاد لكل انواع البكتيريا
To finish I'll just show you the strategy.
لكي انهي سوف اطلعكم على الاستراتيجية
In this one I'm just using the interspecies molecule,
في هذه استخدم فقط الجزيء الذي يصل بين الأصناف
but the logic is exactly the same.
ولكن النظرية هي نفسها.
What you know is that when that bacterium gets into the animal,
الذي تعرفونه هو عند دخول البكتيريا الى جسم حيوان
in this case, a mouse,
في هذه الحاله فأر
it doesn't initiate virulence right away.
لاتقوم بنشر الوباء فوراً
It gets in, it starts growing, it starts secreting
فهي تدخل الجسم وتبدأ بالتكاثر ثم تبدأ بأفراز
its quorum sensing molecules.
الجزيء المسؤل عن ادراك النصاب
It recognizes when it has enough bacteria
وتدرك زمن وصلوها الى العدد الكافي من البكتيريا
that now they're going to launch their attack,
اي الوقت الذي ستقوم فيه بشن الهجوم
and the animal dies.
فتتسبب بقتل الحيوان
What we've been able to do is to give these virulent infections,
ماستطعنا ان نقوم به هو اعطاء هذه العدوى السامة
but we give them in conjunction with our anti-quorum sensing molecules --
ولكن قمنا بضمها مع الجزيئات المسؤلة عن ادراك النصاب
so these are molecules that look kind of like the real thing,
وبالتالي هذه جزيئات تشبه تماما الجزيئات الاصلية
but they're a little bit different which I've depicted on this slide.
ولكنها تختلف قليلا كما هو مصور في هذه الشريحة
What we now know is that if we treat the animal
ما ندركه الان هو انه اذا قمنا بمعالجه الحيوان
with a pathogenic bacterium -- a multi-drug-resistant pathogenic bacterium --
بالبكتريا المسببه للمرض اي البكتريا المعدية والمضادة للعديد من الادوية
in the same time we give our anti-quorum sensing molecule,
بنفس الوقت الذي نقوم به باعطاء الجزيئ المضاد لادراك النصاب
in fact, the animal lives.
في الحقيقه، يبقى الحيوان على قيد الحياه
We think that this is the next generation of antibiotics
نظن ان هذا هو الجيل الجديد من المضادات الحيوية
and it's going to get us around, at least initially,
وهذا ما سوف يساعدنا على تخطي المرحلة، على الاقل كبداية
this big problem of resistance.
مشكله المقاومة الكبيرة
What I hope you think, is that bacteria can talk to each other,
ما أرجو ان تفكرو به، هو ان البكتيريا تتكلم مع بعضها البعض
they use chemicals as their words,
تستخدم مواد كيميائية ككلمات
they have an incredibly complicated chemical lexicon
ولديها قاموس لغوي كيميائي معقد للغاية
that we're just now starting to learn about.
والذي بدأنا حاليا بدراسته و فهمه
Of course what that allows bacteria to do
بالطبع هذا يمنح البكتيريا القدره على
is to be multicellular.
ان تكون متعددة الخلايا
So in the spirit of TED they're doing things together
فبلتالي انطلاقا من روح تيد فهي تقوم بالعمل معاً
because it makes a difference.
لان ذلك يحدث فرقا
What happens is that bacteria have these collective behaviors,
فما يحدث هو أن البكتيريا تتمتع بسلوك جماعي
and they can carry out tasks
كما يمكنهم القيام بمهام
that they could never accomplish
لن تستطيع انجازها
if they simply acted as individuals.
اذا تصرفت ببساطه كأفراد
What I would hope that I could further argue to you
ما أرجوه هو أن أتمكن من اقناعكم
is that this is the invention of multicellularity.
هو هذا الإكتشاف عن العمل بتعدد الخلايا.
Bacteria have been on the Earth for billions of years;
تتواجد البكتيريا على الارض منذ مليارات السنين
humans, couple hundred thousand.
اما الانسان بضعه مئات الألوف تقريبا
We think bacteria made the rules
ونعتقد ان البكتيريا وضعت القوانين
for how multicellular organization works.
عن كيفيه عمل الجماعات متعدده الخلية
We think, by studying bacteria,
نعتقد عن طريق دراستنا للبكتيريا
we're going to be able to have insight about multicellularity in the human body.
سوف نكون قادرين على تشكيل رؤيه حول عمل تعدد الخلية في جسم الانسان
We know that the principles and the rules,
نحن على علم بالمبادئ و القوانين
if we can figure them out in these sort of primitive organisms,
واذا استطعنا ان نفهمها في هذه الكائنات البدائية
the hope is that they will be applied
الامل هو ان نطبقها
to other human diseases and human behaviors as well.
أمراض الإنسان الأخرى وكذلك التصرفات البشرية
I hope that what you've learned
وآمل ان نكون تعلمنا
is that bacteria can distinguish self from other.
ان البكتريا قادره على أن تميز نفسها من البكتيريا الأخرى
By using these two molecules they can say "me" and they can say "you."
عن طريق استخدام جزيئين باستطاعتهما قول "انا" او قول "انت"
Again of course that's what we do,
ومرة أخرى بالطبع هذا ما نقوم به
both in a molecular way,
سواء في طريقة جزيئية
and also in an outward way,
او كما في طريقة الخارج
but I think about the molecular stuff.
ولكن عندما افكر في الامور الجزيئية
This is exactly what happens in your body.
فهذا تماما مايحدث في جسم الانسان
It's not like your heart cells and your kidney cells get all mixed up every day,
هذا لايعني ان خلايا القلب و خلايا الكلى تختلط ببعضها كل يوم،
and that's because there's all of this chemistry going on,
وهذا بسبب وجود كل هذه الكيمياء التي تؤدي عملها
these molecules that say who each of these groups of cells is,
هذه الجزيئات التي تقول كل منها ماهي مجموعة الخلايا التي تنتمي اليها
and what their tasks should be.
وما الوظيفة التي يجب ان تقوم بها
Again, we think that bacteria invented that,
مرة أخرى، نعتقد ان البكتيريا هي التي قامت بابتكارها
and you've just evolved a few more bells and whistles,
وقد تطورنا نحن عن هذه الخصائص بعض الشئ
but all of the ideas are in these simple systems that we can study.
ولكن كل الافكار موجودة في هذا النظام البسيط الذي يمكن دراسته
The final thing is, again just to reiterate that there's this practical part,
في النهايه اود ان اكرر ان هنالك الجزء العملي
and so we've made these anti-quorum sensing molecules
فقد قمنا بعمل هذه الجزيئات المضاده لادراك النصاب
that are being developed as new kinds of therapeutics.
والتي يجرى تطويرها كنوع جديد من الادويه
But then, to finish with a plug for all the good and miraculous bacteria
ولكن ايضا، كي ننهي بفائده للبكتيريا ذات الدور الفعال المساعده للانسان
that live on the Earth,
والتي تعيش على الارض
we've also made pro-quorum sensing molecules.
لقد قمنا بعمل جزيء يدعم عمليه ادراك النصاب
So, we've targeted those systems to make the molecules work better.
ولقد استهدفنا هذه الأنظمة كي نجعل الجزيئات تعمل بصوره افضل
Remember you have these 10 times or more bacterial cells
تذكرو ان لديكم عشره اضعاف اكثر من الخلايا البكتيريه
in you or on you, keeping you healthy.
عليكم او داخل اجسامكم، وتبقيكم بصحة جيدة
What we're also trying to do is to beef up the conversation
ونحاول ايضا على ان نقوي المحادثة
of the bacteria that live as mutualists with you,
بين البكتيريا التي تتعايش معنا في تكافل
in the hopes of making you more healthy,
على امل ان تؤثر ايجابيا في صحتنا
making those conversations better,
العمل على تقويه هذه المحادثات
so bacteria can do things that we want them to do
كي تقوم البكتيريا بعمل مانريدها ان تقوم به
better than they would be on their own.
بصوره احسن من لوكانت تقوم بهذه الاعمال لوحدها
Finally, I wanted to show you
في النهاية أود ان أريكم
this is my gang at Princeton, New Jersey.
هذه هي عصابتي من جامعه برينستون، نيوجيرسي
Everything I told you about was discovered by someone in that picture.
كل شيء تحدثت عنه هو ناتج عن اكتشاف من احد افراد هذه الصورة
I hope when you learn things,
آمل أنكم تعلمتم أشياءاً
like about how the natural world works --
متل كيفيه عمل عالم الطبيعه
I just want to say that whenever you read something in the newspaper
كنت اود ان اقول انه عندما نقرأ شيئاً في الجريدة
or you get to hear some talk about something ridiculous in the natural world
او نسمع احداً يتكلم عن شيئ سخيف في عالم الطبيعة
it was done by a child.
انه أُنجزعلى يد طفل
Science is done by that demographic.
العلم قائم على تلك الفئة
All of those people are between 20 and 30 years old,
كل هؤلاء الاشخاص تتراوح أعمارهم بين العشرون و الثلاثون
and they are the engine that drives scientific discovery in this country.
وهم المحرك الذي يقود الاكتشافات العلميه في هذا البلد
It's a really lucky demographic to work with.
في الحقيقه هو من حسن حظي العمل مع هذه الديموغرافيه
I keep getting older and older and they're always the same age,
مازلت اتقدم في السن اكبر فاكبر وهم يبقون دوما شبابا.
and it's just a crazy delightful job.
انه عمل جنوني و مبهج في آن واحد.
I want to thank you for inviting me here.
اود ان اشكركم على دعوتي للحضور هنا.
It's a big treat for me to get to come to this conference.
انها متعه كبيره بالنسبه لي ان احضر هذه المحاضره.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thanks.
شكرا.